<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honesty and true zeal of the Kings witnesses justified and vindicated against those unchristian-like equivocal protestations of Dr. Oliver Plunkett, asserting in his last speech his own innocency being as great damnation to his soul, as any of his former trayterous and hellish practices against his King and countrey, as breathing them upon the point of death, without any time of repenting the enormity of them with true contrition / by Florence Weyer, Gent.</title>
            <author>Weyer, Florence.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11981397</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11981397</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51846</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51846)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honesty and true zeal of the Kings witnesses justified and vindicated against those unchristian-like equivocal protestations of Dr. Oliver Plunkett, asserting in his last speech his own innocency being as great damnation to his soul, as any of his former trayterous and hellish practices against his King and countrey, as breathing them upon the point of death, without any time of repenting the enormity of them with true contrition / by Florence Weyer, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Weyer, Florence.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Plunket, Oliver, --  Saint, 1629-1681.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51846:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HONESTY AND TRUE ZEAL OF THE Kings Witneſſes Juſtified and Vindicated againſt thoſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christian-like Equivocal Proteſtations of D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Oliver Plunkett,</p>
            <p>Aſſerting in his laſt Speech his own inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; being as great Damnation to his Soul, as any of his former Trayterous and Helliſh Practices againſt his King and Countrey, as breathing them upon the point of Death, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any time of repenting the Enormity of them with true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition.</p>
            <p>By FLORENCE WEYER, Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baldwin,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51846:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51846:2"/>
            <p>THough never condemned by any Judge in this tranſitory world, yet no man can limit himſelf his ſojourning here, from the ſearcher of all hearts and the Judge of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Glory; but muſt ſtand as vigilant and awful not to offend his Creator and Redeemer, as if he were to paſs into another World in the twinkling of an Eye. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope that all true hearts will conſider how I hope for Salvation as well as a dying man: So that I expect upon the Faith of a Chriſtian, they will give credit unto the true conviction of the ſubſequent Aſſertions of Dr. <hi>Plunkett.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Witneſſes were only deſigned for his Life.</hi> To that I anſwer, That the Witneſſes were not deſigned for his life, nor covetous of his blood, well knowing that blood muſt be required for blood, if unjuſtly taken; but were only zealous to diſcharge themſelves of their bounden duty to their Dread Sovereign, his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. 2. <hi>That he was accuſed in</hi> Ireland <hi>of Treaſon and Praemunire.</hi> Which in my judgement he ſhould have ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led High-Treaſon, and that the grandeſt of any yet ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. 3. <hi>That there he was Arraigned and brought to his Tryal.</hi> A very fine <hi>hyſteron proteron,</hi> but if once quitted never arraigned for the ſelf and the ſame fact. 4. <hi>That the Proſecutors, men of flagitious and infamous lives</hi> (as he pleaſed to term them) <hi>voluntarily abſented themſelves.</hi> Wherein the Witneſſes (though not flagitious, ſuch of them as I know) are much to be commended; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt ſtated the caſe with the Judges, what danger it was (leſt the King ſhould get the ſlip) to have the Traytor tryed there, where inevitably he muſt needs be tryed by his own Confederates for the moſt part, who would ſooner hang the Judges than him; thouſands both of Clergy and Lay-men having flocked thither and thereabouts, expecting the event; the Judges were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51846:3"/>well pleaſed to paſs the Tryal till further courſe were taken. Further pretending, <hi>That then at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes of</hi> Dundalke <hi>he had Records and Witneſſes who would evidently convince the Kings Witneſſes, clearly ſhew his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and their wickedneſs.</hi> The nature of thoſe Records he ſpeaks of I do not underſtand; Witneſſes I know he had too many, whoſe intereſt it was as much to defend him as to ranſome their own lives at the higheſt rate imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. What benefit he could reap by thoſe Records I cannot conceive, unleſs they could make out his being before then tryed for the ſaid ſeveral actions of High-Treaſon laid to his charge, which was impoſſible for the ſaid Records to do. Further complaining, <hi>That the Jury here did not know him, nor the quality of the Accuſers.</hi> The firſt fell out well for him, but the latter ill for his Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers: for, were the Jury and all other well-wiſhers of his Majeſty, but acquainted with the real ſincerity of the chiefeſt of thoſe Witneſſes, their preſent and future dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger would be taken into better care, and their neceſſary want would be better ſupplied; but had they known <hi>Plunkett,</hi> they would ſide with him as the Jury in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but would have ordered (if poſſible) his never dying and endleſs tortures, to be ſo preſerved as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all ambitious Uſurpers, and baſe-born aſpirers. Further complaining, <hi>That by reaſon of the uncertainty of the Seas, and the difficulty of getting Copies of Records, his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes could not attain to him in time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray, good Souls, obſerve the prevarication of that Speech, in one place affirming, <hi>He had the ſaid Records in</hi> Dundalke <hi>aforeſaid, about a twelvemonth ago.</hi> In another place ſaying, <hi>He had them ſtill to get.</hi> I aſſure you, if there were any ſuch uſeful Records as he pretended, he wanted not friends enough to take them out all this while: As for his Witneſſes who may be juſtly called the flagitious and infamous rather than the Kings Witneſſes; a parcel of them being moſt Notorious and Trayterous Rebels, were gathered together to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where not getting the Kings ſafe conduct, as they were promiſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51846:3"/>by <hi>Plunkett</hi>'s Solicitors, they all diſperſed to their ſeveral refuges, excepting a matter of four of them that came to this City; who, had they but arrived in ſeaſon, their only evidence would have caſt him. As for his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine Tranſactions, and his writing of Letters to Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes for ſending of forces to invade <hi>Ireland,</hi> I can ſay nothing to them but by hear-ſay, therefore will leave them to be treated of by them who know beſt; only this I will infer, that in Court, which is a thing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently known to the whole aſſembly, he did not much deny his Letter to that effect produced by Mr. <hi>Moyre,</hi> though in his ſaid Speech he ſtands on ſtrong negatives. His Domeſtick actions and contrivances I can relate, whereof I will give ſome ſhort account in their places. Further vowing in his ſaid Speech, <hi>That he never ſent Agent or Agents to</hi> Rome <hi>about any Civil or Temporal affairs.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving confeſſed before the face of the Court that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Kingdom, State, and other Promontories of the Roman Catholick Religion, are ſtraitly bound to keep an Agent there continually. And did only deny, That the ſaid Agents yearly means did not exceed 50 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> which was contrary to the Statutes produced by Mr. <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> under <hi>Plunkett</hi>'s own hand, and confeſſed by him to be his own hand-writing, wherein was enacted, That the ſaid Agent be ſupported in <hi>Rome</hi> by the yearly mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of 500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> Sterling: Grant it were 50 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> judge if 50 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> would maintain yearly ſuch a Sollicitor. Which ſwerving from his confeſſion in Court, are ſtrong arguments to animadvert his ſaid whole Speech to be moſt falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, for <hi>qui Delinquit in uno, Delinquit in toto.</hi> But here <hi>Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kett</hi>'s Evaſion is to be noted, proteſting, <hi>That he did not ſend an Agent about any Civil or Temporal affairs.</hi> Meaning the affairs not to be Civil, as relating to Military, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe intended for Rebellion and Maſſacre; nor to be Temporal, being intended for Spiritual matters, as <hi>ad propagandam fidem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that Mr. <hi>Moyer</hi> hath not ſwore falſe, as <hi>Plunkett</hi> ſays, but moſt true. Further aſſerting, <hi>That he did not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51846:4"/>write to Cardinal</hi> Bullion, <hi>or any of the French Kings Miniſters, neither did any were in that Court ever write to him directly or indirectly of any Plot or Conſpiracy.</hi> Meaning that it was neither Plot nor Conſpiracy to reduce that Kingdom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their prerogative, as of antient right belonging to them, which is an indiſputable opinion of the major part of that Land. <hi>That he never employed Captain</hi> Con-O-Neill <hi>to the French King or any of his Miniſters, that he never wrote to him, nor ever received Letters from him, and that he never ſaw him but once, and ſpoke not ten words to him.</hi> In this I pray let ſelf-reaſon convince the ſtupid: Suppoſe that Captain <hi>Con-O-Neill,</hi> the ſon of General <hi>Owen-O-Neill,</hi> being the beſt warriour, the chiefeſt Head-piece, and ſole ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader of all the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> and the ſaid Captain himſelf being a ſtout Souldier, a great Courtier, and a Traveller, newly come out of <hi>France</hi> in the Equipage of a noble Peer of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> meeting as it were but by meer accident, the Iriſh Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and Metropolitan in the Convent of the Franciſcan Fryers of <hi>Armagh,</hi> judge whether it be credible but more than ten words ſhould paſs between them, being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 48 hours, concerning their very travels in Foreign Countreys: But if met of ſet purpoſe, as it was, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Concluſion of that horrid and deteſted Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I hope that then I need not invite you to judge im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially. <hi>Plunkett</hi> adding further, <hi>As for Captain</hi> Neill<hi>'s being in</hi> Charlemount <hi>or</hi> Dungannon, <hi>I never ſaw him in them Towns, nor ever knew of his being in thoſe places.</hi> I pray, good Reader, mark theſe Proteſtations of a dying man and a worthy Prelate, the ſaid Convent where he and Captain <hi>Neill</hi> had an Intermedium, being within four miles of either of thoſe Forts, and <hi>Plunkett</hi> never knew of his being in thoſe places. 'Tis to be obſerved, that <hi>Plunkett</hi> was not charged to have been within thoſe very Forts with Captain <hi>Neill,</hi> for it was determined that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Terrel,</hi> the ſaid Captain <hi>Neill</hi>'s Brother, <hi>John-O-Neill</hi> Guardian of the ſaid Convent, <hi>Patrick-O-Donnelly</hi> Prieſt, and others, ſhould repair to view the Scituation and Fortifications of thoſe Forts. To ſpend no time idle,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51846:4"/>Captain <hi>Neill</hi> and <hi>Plunkett</hi> betook themſelves a contrary way: <hi>Terrel,</hi> with the reſt of the Truſtees, having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged their truſt, returned back to the ſaid Convent the very ſame day. I hope all true hearts will imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally judge whether the Depoſitions of Mr. <hi>Moyre</hi> as eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs of theſe paſſages be not moſt true or not. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proteſting, <hi>That he never levied any money for a Plot or Conſpiracy, nor ever received any from the Clergy upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi> Meaning thereby as before mentioned; that in their opinion it was neither Plot nor Conſpiracy, to bring that Countrey into their ſecond ſubjection. I pray conſtrue his meaning, and equivocal expreſſions, and ſee if the Depoſitions of Mr. <hi>Duffy</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ma-Clave,</hi> (the former ſerving as Curate to a certain Pariſh Prieſt, collecting and paying Vice-Paſtors the Subſidy-Charge impoſed on the Pariſh of <hi>Faghort</hi> in the County of <hi>Lowth</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the other Vicar of the Pariſh of <hi>Aghen-mallen,</hi> ſatisfying his divident proportion) be not true and not falſe, as he ſays. Further ſaying, <hi>That he never received ought from any Clergy-man in</hi> Ireland <hi>but what was due to him by ancient cuſtom for maintenance, and what his predeceſſors theſe hundred years paſt, received; nay, that he received leſs than many of them.</hi> To which I anſwer, that by no way leſs; For firſt, he was ſo penurious greedy, that leſs than his due by one farthing would not ſatisfie him. Secondly, his Symony and compulſive bribes did far exceed the maintenance of his predeceſſors, for that all his Laws were grounded on this only Maxime, The weightieſt Purſe the beſt and largeſt Pariſh: And although at his firſt intruding to the management of his Primacy, the Clergy and Layety of that Countrey were very tractable, yet within ſhort time he had ſo hood-winked them, that he ſet all the Clergy by the ears, and reduced all into the <hi>Chaos antiquum,</hi> that the weakeſt was forced to appeal to Secular Backs, which bred ſuch a Diſſention and hoſtility amongſt his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects, that it grew at laſt unto the temerity of a <hi>Bellum civile,</hi> or a Civil Broil. None was Capable of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Dignity or Pariſh under him, unleſs that <hi>in annuatim,</hi> he was able to purchaſe it at one twelvemonths annuity;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51846:5"/>nor was that Patent of any longer ſtanding than till ſuch time as another Dignitary or Prebendary came and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced the ſaid annuity, then immediately was drawn for him a Leaſe of Ejectment, without any Clauſe of the leaſt ſavings for the Defendant: All the ſatisfactory remedy he could get, was, to be told, That <hi>Plunkett</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a ſlave to his word; which word lies on ſeveral Records <hi>in perpetuum</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Indorſed by many an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and learned man of the Romiſh Clergy, by him through inexplicable Symony utterly deprived, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was Dr. <hi>Fitzſymon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hanzatty,</hi> after taking from him (upon great promiſes to inſtal him Vicar-General of the Dioceſs of <hi>Clogher</hi>) the ſumm of ſixty pieces of Gold, Dr. <hi>Roman Magin,</hi> Dean <hi>Mac-Colin,</hi> Dean <hi>Kelly,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of the very ſelect and choiceſt of that Church. So incomprehenſible was the Symony of this worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch. However, 'tis true, it were poſſible he might dye a true penitent, yet you have hardly obſerved any any man that lived and continued a Traytor, ever dying without a Lye in his mouth. Further denying, <hi>To have cauſed a Liſt to be drawn of the Inhabitants of every reſpective Pariſh from the age of ſixteen to ſixty, for to raiſe an Army, or at leaſt to have them in a readineſs againſt the landing of the French Army; nor to have levied any Subſidies to ſupport them.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I my ſelf have ſeen and peruſed many of his Mandates, both for making the aforeſaid Liſts, and levying the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Nay I have ſeen a very conſiderable ſumm of the money ſo collected, his ſaid Mandates are ſtill extant to be produced. <hi>Patrick Darge-O-Donnelly</hi> Pariſh Prieſt of <hi>Donaghmore</hi> in the County of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> brought in of his collection in <hi>July</hi> laſt, of the Plot-money, the ſumm of nineſcore and ten pounds; I have ſeen the money in the Town of <hi>Caſtle-Blayne.</hi> There are further ſpecial proofs that were by when he paid it to <hi>Plunkett</hi> in <hi>Dundalke,</hi> at the Aſſizes then held there, where he doth moſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alledge to have received his Tryal. Which confirms that the Depoſitions of Mr. <hi>Moyre</hi> are moſt true; and that he, Mr. <hi>Duffy</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ma-Clave</hi> ſwore moſt true, and not falſe, as <hi>Plunkett</hi> ſets out in his Speech.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51846:5"/>Further denying his ſurrounding the Sea-Ports, Forts, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that he was never at <hi>Carlingford</hi> but once, not ſtaying in it above half an hour, nor that Mr. <hi>Duffy</hi> was in his Company; —I anſwer that his Aſſertion is falſly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for he was only taxed for to have ſurrounded the Sea-Ports, Forts, and Havens of the North of Ireland, only which cannot unleſs <hi>Tropice</hi> comprehended all <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereof if few left unſurrounded, he ſent others to view, I likewiſe anſwer, that he was more than once in <hi>Carlingford,</hi> and above half an hour, and that <hi>Duffy</hi> was in his company there, and from thence to the Houſe of one Mr. <hi>Brian Murphy</hi> in <hi>Cooly,</hi> from whence again walking together with <hi>Duffy, Murphy</hi> and <hi>Terence, Murphy</hi> a Secular Prieſt to take the proſpect of Sea and Land; they chanced to paſs by an old ruinated Church, where the ſaid <hi>Brian Murphy</hi> took occaſion to tell <hi>Plunket,</hi> that certain old people Natives of that place could prove, that in their nonage they have ſeen the Burials there as lyable to Church and Clark duties as elſewhere, which cuſtome (ſaid he) is not obſerved now adays, whereat <hi>Plunket</hi> deſired <hi>Murphy</hi> to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry careful in advancing thoſe things, for ſaid he, although they be at preſent poſſeſſed by the heretick Clergy, we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a ſudden reſtoration of them. — In order to his will it was ſo cloſely followed and carryed on by <hi>Murphy,</hi> that the place enjoyeth not the former immunity.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe the teſtimony of the reſt of the company to be of ſufficiency to prove that <hi>Duffy</hi> was in his Company, and hath not ſwore falſe as <hi>Plunket</hi> in his ſaid Speech alledgeth. Further, I hope you will obſerve, if it was poſsible for a Prelate of his calling to have dined in one Houſe, and in another to have drunk his ſhare of ten Bottles of Wine, and all that in half an Houres time; — As for the reſt of the Forts and Sea-Ports, which he viewed or ſent others to view them, and denyeth his ſo doing, I would have the Reader underſtand this to be his Evaſion; that there is hardly ever a City, Fort or Town Corporate in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but takes its Denomination from either a Fort, Ford, Rock, Mount or ſome other particular ſpot of ground, notified in that place, before the building or planting of a City or Town there, as <hi>Dublin,</hi> which takes its Denomination by Authentick <hi>Iriſh</hi> Preſidents, from a Bridge made of wattle hyrdles, to drive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Lyffin</hi> water, the Sheep of a certain rich man by name <hi>Atherne,</hi> then Inhabitant there; <hi>Drogheda</hi> from the like ſubject, <hi>Carrickfergus</hi> from a ſteepy Rock whereon the Caſtle is Built,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51846:6"/>and <hi>Fergus</hi> called the firſt King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the founder of that Caſtle, for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> word <hi>Carrick,</hi> ſignifieth in <hi>Engliſh</hi> a ſteepy Rock. <hi>Liſina Garvy</hi> from a Fort <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Plunket</hi> dare boldly proteſt with ample Conſcience, that he was never in thoſe Towns, as not being within thoſe very particular places, from whence they receive their ſaid ſeveral Denominations, which if a man with ſafe conſcience can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I leave the world to Judge. — Further aſſerting that he was never at any meeting of 300 Gentlemen, in any the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Ardmagh, Monaghan,</hi> or <hi>Cavan;</hi> which negative would extend to an admiration of the truth, were as well known here as in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereas he kept his Provincial Counſels in them Counties, yet his wily Evaſions are to be notified, meaning that all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentlemen in that Province are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated, as not poſſeſſed of any preſent Eſtates or Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; yet for his life he would ſay, but that he was at an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of 300 <hi>Iriſh</hi> Gentlemen by Extraction.</p>
            <p>Further adding in his ſaid Speech, and 'tis well known, that there are not even in all the Province of <hi>Ulſter</hi> 300 Roman Catholicks who had Eſtates, or loſt Eſtates by the late Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, which is a mighty abominable and unpardonable Lye, as evidently indiſputable as the Sun ſits in its Continents. But Gentle Reader, to ſatisfie your mind further, of the late Horrid intended Conſpiracy, you ſhall underſtand, that thoſe who loſt their Eſtates there, 400 or 500 years ago, are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seſſed, with as fervent a thirſt of recovery, as thoſe who loſt it by the late Rebellion; nay the very Danes are ever ſtill deſigned for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further proteſting, that he never knew or heard, that the <hi>French</hi> were to land at <hi>Carlingford,</hi> and that he did believe there were none who ever ſaw <hi>Ireland</hi> even in a Map, but would think it a meer Romance. To which I anſwer, that 'tis to be obſerved the guilt of his horrid Crimes rendered him unmindful of his former ſagacity; ſo that he muſt needs bring out this uncolorable Lye, to diſcover the Palpability of that his whole laſt Speech, to be moſt maliciouſly falſe, and grounded only to bring revenge and aſperſion upon the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; for truly the very <hi>Iriſh</hi> Etimology of the word <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingford</hi> verifies the Haven to be doubtleſs as good (unleſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51846:6"/>ſomewhat narrow) as any in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland.</hi> But to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it, will not be ſo ſatisfactory to you, as the experience of the Haven.</p>
            <p>As to the Word it conſiſts of three ſyllables thus, <hi>Cath-ar-ling, Cath</hi> ſignifieth a Fight Fought, <hi>ar,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>on,</hi> and <hi>ling</hi> the ſtream or Water, <hi>viz. Cartharling</hi> in <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingford</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and taketh that name from a great Fight fought on that Water, juſt at the Foot of the Caſtle between the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and the <hi>Danes.</hi> I aſſure that any of His Majeſties beſt Ships even at low water, may ride into the Bay there till it hook the very Caſtle wall. <hi>Oliver</hi> the firſt Uſurper had no ſmall Fleet with which, notwithſtanding the Block-houſe with all its Artillery, playing as faſt as a ſhower of Arrows, and all other the Fortifications there, he landed in that place, which I hope confirms the Evidence of the Witneſſes not to be Romance.</p>
            <p>However <hi>Oliver</hi> the ſecond muſt be then no greater Slave to his word, then during the reſt of his life, it being his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon apology when reproved about his Lies. Nevertheleſs, the ſelf partial are very apt and inclinable to believe the laſt proteſtations of that dying Patriarch, and ſweet Traytor, who never before during his life time could tell any truth.</p>
            <p>Further alleadging, that if he ſhould confeſs theſe crimes, or to have acknowledged the raiſing of Seventy Thouſand Men in <hi>Ulfter,</hi> or even in all <hi>Ireland,</hi> it being well known that all the revenues of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Spiritual and Temporal poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seſſed by His Majeſties Subjects, are ſcarce able to raiſe and maintain an Army of Seventy Thouſand men; or the deſign of landing the <hi>French</hi> at <hi>Carlingford,</hi> no wiſe man that knows <hi>Ireland</hi> would believe him, all would laugh at him, no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Jury would find him Guilty of the Indictment.</p>
            <p>It is a great truth, that <hi>Ireland</hi> was never ſince the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, ſo populous as it is in theſe later days, and conſequently indiſputably true, that <hi>Ulſter</hi> could raiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Thouſand Men, ſet the reſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> aſide, but mark herein how delivering the words poſſeſſed by His Majeſties Subjects, hath betrayed his Equivocations and mental reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as meaning His Sacred Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain</hi> not to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51846:7"/>be Supreme King of that Land, but the Pope, for that <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naghy</hi> M. <hi>Brian</hi> the laſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Kings, being defeated by conqueſt brought the Crown out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and delivered it to the Pope, ſo that depriving the King of <hi>England</hi> of his Right and Prerogative of <hi>Ireland,</hi> his Subjects there can raiſe but a ſmall army. I pray obſerve the proteſtations of that worthy Patriarch.</p>
            <p>Yet I grant, that no wiſe man of his own Helliſh and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Crew would reſemble to believe him; that they would diſſemble to laugh at him, for he is a fool that would not cover his own nakedneſs, as alſo 'tis very true that no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Proteſtant Jury would Caſt him. Adding further, that the Jury in <hi>Ireland</hi> would no more believe him, then they would believe that he had flown in the air from <hi>Dublin</hi> to <hi>Holy-head.</hi> — Which is an extraordinary Hyperbolical lye; for that the Jury there, ſuch as he would have himſelf tryed with all did believe, and (as Guilty of the Fact) was well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in their hearts of the one, though they would proceed contrariwiſe, but of the other could not be ſatisfied by proof or otherwiſe. Yet <hi>Plunket</hi> muſt not be a Slave to his word.</p>
            <p>In his ſaid laſt Speech he denies to have been ever ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Four Laymen of the Witneſſes, <hi>viz. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> M. <hi>Moyer,</hi> the two <hi>Neals</hi> and <hi>Hanlon,</hi> meaning me the firſt of the Four; to that point I can ſay nothing, my Sirname being <hi>Weyer,</hi> and not <hi>Mac Moyer,</hi> with whom, <hi>Plunket</hi> was very well acquainted ſince firſt he went to <hi>Ireland,</hi> which I could make good by a thouſand Witneſſes if requiſite; the firſt time that ever I met him, was in the Fryery of <hi>Ardmagh,</hi> where, was no leſs then three or four hundred Speculators, he did diſcourſe with me aſide: In his going away, I conveyed him a good piece of his Journey, he further diſcourſed with me, in ſeveral Aſſemblies held by him at the Houſe of <hi>George Blyke</hi> of the <hi>Fives,</hi> in purſuance of contriving that his deteſted conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and very often made much of me in his own houſe, which kindneſs I conjecture to have rather extended from fear that I ſhould appear againſt him, then from any hearty good will. I pray how could this man have the Impudency of denying to be acquainted with me? Becauſe he muſt not be a Slave to his Word.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51846:7"/>
Yet I ſhall paſs over all further Juſtification on my own account, he having vomited as grand Lies as that, arguing the Judges of Injuſtice done to him, which I leave to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es themſelves to vindicate or forgive.</p>
            <p>He adds further, that there was a <hi>Judas</hi> among the Twelve Apoſtles, and a Wicked man called <hi>Nicholas</hi> amongſt the Seven Deacons; by which expreſſions it may be eaſily underſtood, how that ſweet Traitor pretends to be another Chriſt on Earth, calling the Witneſſes another <hi>Judas</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Nicholas,</hi> deeming himſelf to be convicted by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, which property of <hi>Judas,</hi> he ſhould of all right attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to himſelf and his confederates, who did intend (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by Gods Providence obſtructed) to betray his true and lawful King to the hands of his Enemies, and to Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre all his true Subjects, wherefore I may boldly return him that which he tells of <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Nicholas</hi> for <hi>Exemplo tangi non propriore poteſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet this man who thus fabricated the death of his Sacred Majeſty; to ſubvert the preſent Government, the tranquility of His Majeſties true and Loyal Subjects, who cauſed ſo many diſorders among thoſe of the Roman Catholick Clergy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Charge, ſo much miſgovernment within his diſtricts, living by Treachery and Symony, even to the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their rights, many an honeſt and worthy Prelate not by him corruptible, muſt dye a Sanctified Martyr, redoubling Guilt upon Guilt, till the pangs of death overcame his laſt Breath.</p>
            <p>Gentle Reader, I have here made apparantly appear unto the whole world, how undeſervedly the Kings Witneſſes were Impeached by that Speech of Dr. <hi>Oliver Plunket,</hi> I have juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their innocency, with what true zeal and integrity they proceeded.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Plunket</hi> pretending nothing to be ſo purgative as a Dying mans laſt proteſtations, upon which principle equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and with ſecret Evaſions aſſerting to have never acted any thing impugnant to His Majeſties Laws, Crown, Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Regal Government, there are Thouſands in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and thoſe to be ingeniouſly multiplied by none
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51846:8"/>of the vulgar Arethmeticians, who will not ſcruple abounding with his accuſtomary indulgences, to ſwallow the greateſt of all Oaths to atteſt the unqueſtionable verity of thoſe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations; and that for the enſuing reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. To purchaſe their own Necks from the Halter.</p>
            <p n="2">2d, For that it is their impregnable opinion, that it is more meritorious to dye involved with Mr. Perjury then to diſcover the Guilt of their diſloyal and factious Crew, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to advance arbitrary Government, and that even to the utter extinguiſhing of the Royal Line.</p>
            <p n="3">3d, To darken the worth and repute of the Diſcoverers of the Plot, who may be Juſtly termed the ſecond Ark, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared againſt that execrable intended deluge and devaſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="4">4th, Thinking to vilifie the many good Services to be yet accompliſhed by them.</p>
            <p n="5">5th, To render them ridiculous, bring them into a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Odium,</hi> and that which is the grandeſt Policy, to diſcourage all true loyal Hearts for the future, from attempting any ſuch bold and reſolute undertakings, as the preſervation of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Progeny, and His Majeſties unfeignedly true Subjects.</p>
            <p>However, let them cenſure the Witneſſes as they will, certainly they cannot be indued with ſo much impudency as to averr, that the ſupporting of an Agent in <hi>Rome</hi> to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Popery, and Forraign Forces, to diſenthrone His Majeſty is not High Treaſon, and puniſhable by the Kings Laws; that the enacting of ſeveral Statutes to the ſame purpoſe, produced under his hand, and confesſed by him to be his own hand writing, is not likewiſe high Treaſon and puniſhable <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My dear Souls, what fervency of revenge? and what dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful frency of antipathizing, and inſtigating the inſatiable Fury of the reſt of the Traitors againſt the Witneſſes, poſſeſſed this Traitors heart ſo ſtifly, even at the point of death, to deny thoſe things, which being on his Trial he confesſed, when he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51846:8"/>ſhould ſtand moſt on juſtification, I leave to Judge as well by the Partial, as the Impartial.</p>
            <p>But whereas the devotedly religious at <hi>Tyburn</hi> the firſt of this inſtant, had not their minds generally ſatisfied, as want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Blood enough of Martyr <hi>Plunket</hi> to colour their Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs. I hope if their devotion will ſtill continue, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore condign puniſhment be executed on the reſt of the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in general in <hi>Ireland,</hi> if they will but take paines to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair thither, they may attain to the full of their deſires, by dipping the reſt of their Handkerchiefs in the Blood of many more of the reformed fellow Martyrs of <hi>Plunket,</hi> dying ſtill with a Lye in their mouths, till they breath their laſt Gaſp.</p>
            <p>Now to be brief, I proteſt by the Faith of a Chriſtian, I could inſert a great deale more, of both the Treachery and Perniciouſneſs of Dr. <hi>Plunket,</hi> apt to infect curious Ears, but thinking this to be ſufficient to confute his Lyes, and ſatisfy the ſtupidity of the indifferent, I do not deſire to bellow far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time on the Object. 'Tis well known, that in general we have many implacable Enemies in our own Country, and I my ſelf, moſt of all, ſo that we need not undeſervedly have any more in this Country, yet we are generally hated by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as ſuſpected to be of the number of the Earl of <hi>Shaftes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> his Proſecutors.</p>
            <p>Therefore, theſe are to declare, that Mr. <hi>Moyer,</hi> Mr. <hi>Duffy,</hi> I my ſelf, nor none of our Society would ſpare his Lordſhip, had we but known him Guilty of any high Treaſon to our knowledge; and further, that we have never known him to have infringed His Majeſties Laws, neither do we uſe of courſe to accuſe any, but this infamy we know, to have extended from a certain Pariſite, who for great ſumms of Money re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, promiſed to invalidate our evidence, to the ſaving of <hi>Plunkets</hi> life, who failing therein, indeavoreth to obſcure our Names, to bring upon us the high Diſpleaſure of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Commonalty of this Kingdom, and laboureth to foment all turbulency by atteſting his own Fidelity, but I hope that within ſhort time he ſhall receive his <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> by the hands of <hi>Katch,</hi> at the foot of Mount <hi>Tyburn,</hi> but let <hi>Charon</hi> then have a care of Sinking his Boat by ferrying over the Stygian
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51846:9"/>ſtreams to Prince <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> that inconſiderable draught, the maſter Piece of all the <hi>Europian</hi> Knaves.</p>
            <p>And we do now before the divine Majeſty of Heaven fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and laſtly declare, that what we have done in diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the late horrid Plot, was neither for ſelf preſervation, nor expectation of any worldly Lucre, but from the real and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Allegiance we owe unto His ſacred Majeſty, and our natural Love unto His Loyal Subjects, from which, the very fear of death, the contriving devices of my Enemies, nor the greateſt tortors of Execution ſhall never withdraw me nor mine, but will expoſe my ſelf, and mine, with all my Soul, Heart, Hand, and Subſtance, to all imaginary hazards in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of His Majeſties Service, and maintaining of his Laws, and Government; <hi>Pulchrum &amp; decorum eſt pro Patra mori, multo vero pulchrius pro Rege;</hi> And for my tuition I throw my ſelf on the mercy and providence of the Almighty; and the wanted care of His Sacred Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which, is moſt humbly repreſented to the candid ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of the impartial, by their moſt humble and moſt faithful Servant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Florence Weyer.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 26th. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
